Jacob Gerhard Koch Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Jacob Gerhard Koch Papers 1783-1941 (bulk 1783-1839)
Koch, Jacob Gerhard
130 items
6 containers plus 2 oversize
2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Merchant and marine insurance broker. Correspondence, letterbooks, diary, account books, ledgers, inventories, indexes, receipts, and miscellaneous documents relating to Koch’s investment business in Philadelphia, Amsterdam, and Alexandria, Va.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Buck, Charles Nicholas, 1775-1851.; Koch, Jacob Gerhard.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Germany.; Marine insurance--Europe.; Marine insurance--Latin America.; Marine insurance--Netherlands--Amsterdam.; Marine insurance--North America.; Marine insurance--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Marine insurance--Virginia--Alexandria.; Merchants--Europe.; Merchants--Latin America.; Merchants--Netherlands--Amsterdam.; Merchants--North America.; Merchants--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Merchants--Virginia--Alexandria.
Places
Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; Hamburg (Germany)--History.; Paris (France)--Description and travel.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.
Occupations
Insurance brokers.; Merchants.
Provenance
The papers of Jacob Gerhard Koch, merchant and marine insurance broker, were acquired by the Library of Congress in 1942 by purchase and gift of Samuel Moyerman.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Jacob Gerhard Koch are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jacob Gerhard Koch span the years 1783-1941 with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1783-1839. They consist of correspondence, letterbooks, diary, account books, ledgers, inventories, indexes, receipts, memoirs of Charles Nicholas Buck published in 1941, and miscellaneous documents.
The collection relates chiefly to Koch’s business dealings as a merchant and marine insurance broker in Amsterdam, 1787-1790, Alexandria, Virginia, 1790-1792, and Philadelphia, 1792-1817, and reflects his varied business dealings in North America, Europe, and Latin America. Much of the collection is in Dutch, although Koch also wrote in English and French. The diary documents a trip by Koch to Paris, 1817-1818, and reflects Parisian social life as well as financial transactions. Additional material in the collection refers to the liquidation of Koch’s estate following his death in 1830.
Container List
- Account books (Box 1)
  - Index (Box 1)
  - 1783-1798 See also Oversize, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1799-1835, (5 folders) (Box 2)
- Correspondence (Box 3)
  - 1783-1809, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1811-1848, (7 folders) (Box 4)
- Diary, 1817-1818 (Box 4)
- Estate documents, 1830-1835, (3 folders) (Box 5)
- Marine insurance, 1796-1812, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Memoirs of Charles N. Buck: Interspersed With Private Anecdotes and Events of the Times from 1791 to 1841, 1941 (Box 5)
- Memoranda, 1787 See Oversize (Box 5)
- Receipts, 1798-1799, 1831-1839, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Account books, 1787-1798, (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Memoranda, 1787, (Container 5) (Box OV 2)